# **RUSIRU THUSHARA**

🔁 <u>thusharakart@gmail.com</u> 🕴 372/1, Opalla, Govinna, Horana, Sri Lanka 🔍 +94 71 302 2214

portfolio

🔝 linkedin/rusiru-thushara 🔛 github/thusharakart 🕕 hackerrank/thusharakart

#### **PROFILE**

A final year computer engineering undergraduate with national-level hackathon wins since 2019 and over 3 years of experience in software development. A quick learner with a strong fundamental knowledge in algorithmic programming, computer vision and a passion for finding simple, innovative solutions to complex real-world problems.

# **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

Computer Vision

Self-Supervised Learning

Open World

Video Modeling

Bio Informatics

# **EXPERIENCE**

# Wadduwage Lab, Harvard University, USA

Jan 2022 - Present

Remote Research Fellow - Full Time Internship

Developed deep learning-based object detection algorithms for DNA damage repair toxicology assays to detect gamma H2AX foci in cellular nuclei images and detecting and quantifying homologous recombination events in rare fluorescent mutant cells deep within the tissue of RaDR mice.

## BioMedInfo Lab, University of North Florida, USA

Jan 2022 - Present

External Research Intern - Part Time

Developing deep learning based algorithms for Automated Protein Function Prediction on Human Phenotype Ontology.

#### SternX Engineering (Pvt) Limited

March 2021 - Present

Software Team Lead - Self Employed

Team leader of an eight-member software developer team who follows Scrum methodologies to deliver web and mobile applications for clients.

#### Instructor and Teaching Assistant | University of Peradeniya

2020 - Present

CO322: Data Structures and Algorithms for 3rd year Computer Engineering undergraduates

CO324: Network and Web Application Design for 3rd year Computer Engineering undergraduates

CO321: Embedded Systems for 3rd year Computer Engineering undergraduates

CO253: Programming and Networking for Electrical and Electronic Engineering undergraduates

GP106: Computing for all 1st year undergraduates

# **EDUCATION**

## University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka

Nov. 2017 - Present

Undergraduate in B.Sc. Engineering(Hons.) Computer Engineering CGPA: 3.80/4.00

## SPARK X Professional Development Program | Spark Academy, Sri Lanka

Mar 2021 - Sep 2021

A 6-month industry readiness program for software engineers that includes technical modules like developing and delivering real-world applications, creative problem solving, and soft skills like empathy, communication, leadership, professionalism, and ethics. Earned a full scholarship during the selection process.

#### **MOOCs**

Deep Learning Specialization   deeplearning.ai   Coursera	2020
Al for Medicine Specialization   deeplearning.ai   Coursera	2020
Data Structures and Algorithms Specialization   UC San Diego   Coursera	2020
AWS Computer Vision: Getting started with GluonCV   AWS   Coursera	2020

#### **HONORS & AWARDS**

1st Place of Code Squad 3.0 (of 150+ teams) 6 hour competitive programming competition for university undergraduates in Sri Lanka.	Nov. 2022
2nd Runner up of MoraXtreme 7.0 (of 180+ teams)	Oct. 2022
12 hour competitive programming competition for university undergraduates in Sri Lanka.	OCI. 2022
5th National rank of IEEEXtreme 16.0 (of 6300+ global teams)	Oct. 2022
24 hour competitive programming competition for university undergraduates worldwide.	001. 2022
1st Runner up of MoraXtreme 6.0 (of 180+ teams)	Oct. 2021
12 hour competitive programming competition for university undergraduates in Sri Lanka.	002021
1st Runner up of Douthan 1.0 (of 80+ teams)	Feb. 2021
12 hour competitive programming competition for university undergraduates in Sri Lanka.	
208th world rank of IEEEXtreme 15.0 (of 5500+ global teams)	Oct. 2021
24 hour competitive programming competition for university undergraduates worldwide.	
1st, 2nd, 1st Country Rank in Hack the Interview IV,V,VI (Asia Pacific)	2020
60 hours competitive coding contest on hackerrank	
Placed 1st, 2nd, 1st country rank and 88/4353, 343/3077, 195/2530 respectively in Asia Pacific region	
2nd Runner up of HackDown 2020 (of 200+ teams)   Competitive programming competition	Apr. 2020
2nd Runner up of hackStat 2.0 (of 90+ teams)	Oct. 2019
Competition in data analysis and prediction on an insurance data set.	
2nd Runner up of UoJCoders v1.0 (of 100+ teams)	March 2019
Competitive programming competition for university undergraduates in Sri Lanka.	
Top 20 National rank of IEEEXtreme 14.0 (of 2000+ global teams)	Oct. 2020
24 hour competitive programming competition for university undergraduates worldwide.	
1680th global rank of Facebook Hacker Cup 2020 (of 32500+ global participants)	July 2020
Top 20 country rank of Google Code Jam, Hash Code, Kick Start	2019 - 2020
Gold Medal in Sri Lankan Physics Olympiad   National Rank - 2nd, Score : 96/100  An annual competition held among high school students to select delegations for the APhO and IPhO.	2016

## **PROJECTS**

## **Open World Object Detection and Discovery**

2022 - Present

Final Year Thesis Project

Advisors - Prof. Salman Khan, Prof. Roshan Ragel, Eng. Gihan Jayatilake

- Investigation of self-supervised, contrastive learning approaches on open-world object detection for unknown object clustering.
- Usage of Vision Transformers for object detection with incremental learning.

## Deep Learning based Algorithms for Gamma H2AX Foci Detection and Analysis

2022 - Present

Advisors - Dr. Dushan N. Wadduwage, Prof. Bevin P. Engelward

- Investigation on leveraging deep learning approaches for detecting and quantifying homologous recombination events in rare fluorescent mutant cells deep within the tissue of RaDR mice
- Usage of deep learning architectures for object detection, classification, and segmentation

## **Protein Function Prediction with Human Phenotype Ontology**

2022 - Present

Advisors - Prof. Indika Kahanda

- Exploring deep learning approaches for categorize human abnormal phenotypes and their semantic relationships.
- Usage of Graph Transformer Networks(GTNs) for predicting HPO annotations of human protein.

#### Advisors - Dr. Upul Jayasinghe, Eng. Sampath Deegalla Applying deep neural networks for estimating the depth map, surface normals, and surface curvature from RGB images. 2021 Fuzzy Based Recommendation System for Research Area Selection Advisors - Dr. Upul Jayasinghe Developed a fuzzy-based recommendation system that suggests suitable research areas for students depending on the skills and interests of the student and the scope of the research area of the supervisors. **Swarm Robots Platform** 2021 Obstacle bots that are localized with an overhead camera setup with the capability of positioning themselves without collisions forming challenging patterns. Technologies: Diango, OpenCV, Numpy, Three.is, CSS, HTML, MQTT, GRPC Techniques: Stochastic gradient descent, PID, Image processing, Encryption National Covid 19 Management System 2021 Full-stack web application showcasing country level, district level, hospital level, and overall patient statistics of daily Covid-19 updates and the patient management system. Technologies: Java, Spring Boot, Spring Data JPA, Hibernate, Spring Security, React, PostgreSQL 2020 Airport Ticket Booking System Web application and Mobile Application with a Database Management System for passengers and airports. Technologies: Dart, MySQL, PHP, HTML, CSS **Crossword Puzzle Game** 2021 An instant game developed for Facebook focusing children where they can select and solve a crossword puzzle. Technologies: **React.js** TECHNICAL STRENGTHS Python, Java, C/C++, JavaScript Modeling Languages PyTorch, Scikit-Learn, NumPy, Pandas Frontend Reactis, Bootstrap, HTML/CSS Mobile Development Native Android, Flutter **Databases** Backend MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB Spring Boot, Nodejs, Expressjs, Django EXTRA CURRICULAR Teaching Data Structures and algorithms with Hackers' Club for all undergraduates at UoP 2020 2020 Creating coding problems for five HackerRank programming competitions of UoP 2019 - 2020 Volunteer teaching | Maths, Science and English at Omaththa College, Mathugama 2008 - 2016 Captain | Main Chess Team, Taxila Central College, Horana, Sri Lanka Have won multiple achievements including 1st runner-up in district level Senior House Captain | Taxila Central College, Horana, Sri Lanka 2015

Prediction of Depths, Normals, and Surface Curvature from RGB Images using CNNs

#### REFERENCE

Dr. Dushan N. Wadduwage <u>wadduwage@fas.harvard.edu</u> Ph.D. (NUS), John Harvard Distinguished Science Fellow, Center for Advanced Imaging, Harvard University, Massachusetts Hall, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA +1 (857) 253-1083

Prof. Roshan Ragel <u>roshanr@pdn.ac.lk</u>
Head of Dept. of Computer Engineering,
Faculty of Engineering, University of Peradeniya,
Peradeniya, Sri Lanka.
+94 (77) 385-7755

2021